Chapter 23. The Lee Shore.
Some chapters back one Bulkington was spoken of, a tall new landed mariner
encountered in New Bedford at the inn.
When, on that shivering winter's night, the Peekquad thrust her vindictive
boughs into the cold, malicious waves, who should I see standing at her helm
but Bulkington. I looked with sympathetic awe and fearfulness upon the
man, who in mid-inter just landed from a 4 years dangerous voyage, could so
unrestingly push off again for still another tempestuous term. The land
seemed scorching to his feet.
Wonderfulst things are ever the unmentionable. Deep memories yield no
epitaps. This 6-in chapter is the stoneless grave of Bulington. Let me
only say that it fared with him as with the stormtossed ship that miserably
drives along the lured land. The port would fain give sucker. The port is
pitiful. In the port is safety, comfort, hearthstone, supper, warm blankets,
friends, all that's kind to our mortalities. But in that gale, the port,
the land, is that ship's dyrus jeopardy.
She must fly all hospitality. One touch of land, though it but graze the keel,
would make her shudder through and through. With all her might she crowds
all sail offshore. in so doing fights against the very winds that feain would
blow her homeward seeks all the lashed seas landlessness again for refuge's
sake for Laurenly rushing into peril her only friend her bitterest foe
know ye now Bulkington glimpses do you seem to see of that mortally intolerable
truth that all deep earnest thinking is but the intrepid effort of the soul to
keep the open independence of her sea while the wildest winds of heaven and
earth conspire to cast her on the treacherous slavish shore.
But as in landlessness alone resides highest truth, shoreless, indefinite as
God, so better it is to perish in that howling infinite than be in gloriously
dashed upon the lee, even if that were safety. For wormlike then, oh, who would
craven crawl to land? Terrors of the terrible. Is all this agony so vain?
Take heart. Take heart, O Bington. Bear thee grimly, demigod. Up from the spray
of thy ocean perishing. Straight up leaps thy apotheiois.